Clemens, S.L. mss. 1867-1944 LMC 2433
Lilly Library
Clemens, S.L. mss.
1867-1944
Lilly Library
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.
LMC 2433
70 Items
The Clemens, S.L. mss., 1867-1944, consists of correspondence and other materials of Samuel L. Clemens, better known as the author Mark Twain.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Clemens, 1835-1910, was an American author and humorist best known for his novel The Adventures of Tom Sawyer (1876) and its sequel, The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (1885).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondents include: Norman Hapgood, George Brinton McCleelan Harvey, Merle Johnson, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Melville Elijah Stone, and Charles Henry Webb.
Writings and accompanying materials include manuscripts for "The Quaker city holy excursion, chapter 36 of The gilded age"; A Tramp Abroad, Sunrise on Mount Rigi, chapter 29; Following the equator, unpublished portion of chapter 51; a note and seven photographs of Clemens depicting "the progress of a moral purpose through the mind of the human race's Oldest Friend," Aug. 1906; two autograph signatures written in blottentot; and brief notes.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2011
Authors, American--Correspondence; Correspondence; Letters; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908 --Correspondence.; Webb, Charles Henry, 1834-1905 --Correspondence.; Stone, Melville Elijah, 1848-1929 --Correspondence.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910. Correspondence.; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937; Harvey, George Brinton McClellan, 1864-1928; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910. Tramp abroad.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910. Gilded age.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910. Innocents abroad.
- I. Correspondence. (Box 1)
  General
  Some folders may include accompanying materials.
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Woodford, Stewart Lyndon, 1882, Dec. 14 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Chatto & Windus, 1893, Aug. 5 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to MacAlister, Mr., 1897, Apr. 14; (typescript) (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Mr. Harper, 1898, Aug. 30 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Robt. H. Ingersoll & Bro., 1901, May 21 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Mr. Parsons, 1907, Jul. 29 (Box 1)
  - Paine, Albert to Johnson, Merle, 1922, Dec. 15 (Box 1)
  - Shrimplin, W.B. to Indiana Historical Society, 1944, Oct. 4 (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne. Fragment...of a comment on people...telling jokes, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Two autograph signatures, blottentot style, with photograph, Undated. (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne to Stedmund, Edmund Clarence, Undated. (Box 1)
- II. Writings. (Box 1)
  - A Tramp Abroad by Mark Twain. Chapter 29: Sunrise on Mount Rigi., 1880; Autograph Manuscript. (bound) (Box 1)
  - A Tramp Abroad by Mark Twain. Chapter 29: Sunrise on Mount Rigi., Typescript. (Box 1)
  - The Gilded Age by Mark Twain. Chapter 36., [1873]; Holograph Manuscript. (Box 1)
  - The Gilded Age by Mark Twain. Chapter 36., Typescript. (Box 1)
  - The Progress of a Moral Purpose. Autograph Note with Seven Photographs., 1906 (Box 1)
  - Following the Equator. Chapter 51 (unpublished portion)., 1897 (Box 1)
  - The Quaker City: Holy Land Excursion an unfinished play by Mark Twain. (Privately Printed:, 1867; 1927.) (Box 1)